创世之初 冥冥之中
In the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...
时间 空间和物质
of time, space, and matter.
现在 所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了我们生存的限制
beyond the limits of our existence...
这个空间我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
它们漫步在行星的地表
They roam the planetary surface...
穿梭于水下
fly under water...
翱翔在空中
and soar through the heavens.
然而这不是地球上的野生动物游猎
But this is no wildlife safari on planet Earth.
这是天文级的探险
This is an expedition of astronomical proportions.
这里看出去一切良好
Everything looks good from here.
好 收到
Okay, we copy that.
一旦人类发现自己并不孤单
When the human race discovers it is not alone...
那么我们的宇宙兄弟姐妹们都会是什么模样呢?
what will our cosmic brothers and sisters look like?
为了回答这个问题 主要的天文学家和太空生物学家
To answer this question, leading astronomers and astrobiologists...
将进化原理和物理学运用于
have applied the principles of evolution and physics...
有可能在宇宙中发现的五种类型的外星世界
to five types of alien worlds likely to be found in the cosmos.
这些是有可能存在的生物
These are the creatures that could be out there.
准备好 来一次星际游猎
Prepare to take an intergalactic safari...
睁大眼睛 来看看《陌生的面孔》
and peer directly into the eyes of "Alien Faces."
宇宙:陌生的面孔
宇宙
The universe...
星际庇护所
an intergalactic sanctuary...
居住着数十亿个星系
of billions of galaxies...
数万亿颗恒星
and trillions of stars.
难道它只是死气腾腾的荒芜之地
Could it only be a lifeless, barren wasteland...
到处是伽马射线暴
of gamma-ray bursts...
燃烧的恒星
burning stars...
黑洞?
and black holes?
抑或有生命存在于地球以外的宇宙天堂里呢?
Or does life exist beyond Earth in this cosmic paradise?
会不会外星人也盯着我们 琢磨着一个古老的问题
Do alien faces gaze towards us, pondering the age-old question...
我们孤独吗?
are we alone?
科学家仍然在搜索着
Scientists are still searching...
我们地球以外生命发来的首个信号
for the first signs of life beyond our planet...
但是很多人相信它就在那里 等待着我们去发现
but many are convinced it's out there, waiting for us to find it.
然而立足地球 要是存在的话 那会是啥模样呢?
But what on Earth, if anything, would it look like?
利用地球科学 逻辑学 进化理论的有力结合
With a potent mix of earth science, logic, and the theory of evolution...
计算机图形艺术家已经能够
computer graphic artists are able...
拿出某些外星生命的模样
to bring some of these alien faces to life.
为了亲眼目睹这些外星人世界
And to come face to face with these extraterrestrial creations...
我们将展开一场梦幻游猎
we will embark on a fantasy safari...
进入宇宙尚未探索的地方
through the unexplored reaches of the universe...
就像是巡游在星际动物园里
like a tourist in an intergalactic zoo.
我们的第一站 假设行星 Eronel
Our first stop, the theoretical planet Eronel.
行星 Eronel是一颗年长的行星
The planet Eronel is an odd planet.
首先 它并不是围绕着我们太阳一般的恒星
First of all, it doesn't circle around a star like our Sun.
它围绕着一颗小红矮星
It circles around a little red dwarf.
那些都是些小恒星
These are tiny stars.
它们有时会是我们太阳大小的五分之一 六分之一
They're sometimes a fifth, a sixth the size of our Sun.
因此 宜居区会非常靠近那颗恒星
So the habitable zone is going to be much closer to that star.
这个宜居区是谜团的关键部分
This habitable zone is a crucial piece of the puzzle...
了解任何一颗行星上的生命进化的关键
when understanding the evolution of life on any alien planet.
一个太阳系里的宜居区就是与恒星的距离
A habitable zone in a solar system is the distance from the star...
在那里 水可以以液态存在于地表
where water can exist as a liquid on the surface.
能从恒星获得足够的热量
It gets enough heat energy from the star...
来获得和保留液态水
to have liquid water and stay liquid water.
液态水是生命起源的基本元素之一
Liquid water is one of the basic elements for life to begin.
但是在Eronel上 宜居区
But on Eronel, the habitable zone...
太靠近这颗熊熊燃烧的气球
is so close to this glowing ball of burning gas...
恒星的引力将Eronel潮汐锁定
the star's gravity causes Eronel to be tidally locked...
极像地球的月球
much like Earth's Moon...
我们始终只能看到月球的一个面
as we only see one side of the lunar surface at all times.
这就意味着Eronel的一半始终是白天
This would mean that half of Eronel is constantly in daylight...
而另一半始终是黑夜
and the other half is constantly in darkness.
在中间 会有一个200英里宽的区域
In the middle, there would be a 200-mile-wide area...
横跨南北两极
that stretches from the north pole to the south pole...
那里就是永恒的曙光
which is in a constant state of twilight.
因此就会让你琢磨
So it makes you wonder...
在这颗行星上 哪里可以发现生命呢?
where would we find life on this planet?
实话实说 你会发现它到处都是
Well, truthfully, you're going to find it everywhere.
但是如果它是在黑暗面
But if it's on the dark side...
生命就已经适应居住在黑暗里了
it's life that's been adapted for living in the dark.
如果是在明亮面
And if it's on the bright side...
生命就已经适应就居住在明亮里了
it's life that's been adapted for living only in the bright side.
而在这个曙光区
And in this twilight zone area...
你会发现两者都适应的生物了
you're going to find creatures that are adapted for both.
它们可以在这个世界的两边自由来去
They can wander and stray into both sides on this world.
它们真的把握了自己的命运
They really control their own destinies...
去想去的地方 去想捕食的地方
in where they want to go and where they want to hunt.
在Eronel上 你会看到有光合有机物
On Eronel, you're going to have a photosynthetic organism...
或许 有可能在海洋环境中
probably, likely in the marine environment...
红藻或细菌
a red alga or a bacteria...
可能适应了摄取红外线
that will be adapted to taking in infrared light...
摄取可以摄取的能量来充当食物
and taking what energy it can out of that and making food.
在陆地上 它或许会成为地衣之类的东西 因为天冷
On land, it would probably be a lichen-like thing because it's cold--
苔藓将会适应的
mosses that would be adapted that way.
你将看到以这些为食的生物
You're going to have organisms that are going to feed off those.
Eronel上的这种藻类代表了一个很长食物链的底部
This algae on Eronel represents the bottom of a very long food chain.
所有东西为了生存都扮演着重要的角色
Everything plays a vital role for survival...
从植物到更大 更复杂的生物
from the plant life to the larger, more complex creatures.
在Eronel上利用这种藻类作为食物来源的一个例子
One example on Eronel that uses this algae as a food source...
就是叫做achom的昆虫
is the insect known as an achom.
achom是一种奇怪的小生物
The achoms are a bizarre little creature.
在地球上 我们知道有所谓的形态变化
On Earth, we know of what we call metamorphosis.
就是生物从一种形态变成另一种形态的奇怪的能力
It's the odd ability of a creature to change...from one shape to another.
我们看到变成蝴蝶
We see it in butterflies.
毛毛虫 在你花园里蚕食
A caterpillar, eating in your garden...
爬上围墙 作茧自缚
will climb up on the fence, spin a cocoon...
几个月后 破茧变成蝴蝶
months later, hatch out into a butterfly.
这些虫子也是这样 但是方法非常奇特
These do that, too, but they do it in a very odd way.
它们看上去活像鳗鱼
They look almost eel-like...
两排鳍分列两侧
with two sets of fins that stick out on either side.
在某些特殊的时候
At some peculiar moment...
它们爬上植物
they move over to some of the plant life...
固定在上面
lock themselves in...
依附在上面 外面形成一个壳
and attach themselves and form a shell around them.
当外壳破裂时
When that shell splits...
出现的东西是我们前所未见的
out comes something that we've never seen before.
攫取水中的氢气
Taking the hydrogen from the water...
分解氢气和氧气
splitting the hydrogen from the oxygen...
充气成一个小气泡
it inflates a little bubble...
它们就升出水面
and they lift right out of the water...
微风吹拂它们 将它们带入高空
the breezes picking them up, carrying them to high altitudes...
把它们散播到星球各地
spreading them out over the planet...
随风飘到曙光区
towards the twilight zones as the breezes move.
它们几乎就像是伞兵从天而降
And they're almost like parachutists coming back down.
一旦achom抵达地面
Once the achoms reach the ground...
它们就立即建造洞穴 作为它们的住所
they immediately create a burrow, where they primarily live.
不过在achom觅食泥土里的垃圾时
But as the achoms scavenge through the dirt for food...
它们又会被食物链的
they are hunted from above...
上一层动物从上方捕食
by one of the next links in the food chain...
那就是peena pod
the peena-pod.
我们在这个星球上看到的
Now, one of the creatures...
最有趣的动物之一就是peena pod
that we'd find most interesting on this world is the peena-pod.
它是一种奇怪的小动物
It's an odd little creature...
因为它的眼睛一直绕道后面
because its eyes wrap all the way around...
所以它可以看到背后的所有动静
so it can see any movement behind it.
在Eronel的曙光区
In the twilight zone of Eronel...
那里会是非常阴冷
it is going to be very dark and cold...
原因就是其母星的光线暗淡
due to the low light of its star...
猎手 甚至被猎者
and the hunters, or even the hunted...
都会发展出猫头鹰一般的大眼睛
will have developed large eyes like owls...
或像地球上的其它夜行性动物
or other nocturnal creatures here on Earth.
不过Eronel上的大多数动物已经发展成
But there is an interesting adaptation...
一个有趣的适应现象
that developed in most creatures on Eronel.
Eronel围绕着M星运转
Eronel orbits an M star.
M星发出的光大多数是红外线
M stars emit most of their light in infrared.
红外线就是那种光
Infrared is the light that--
就是你打开烤箱会感到热的光
It's actually heat that you feel when you open up the oven.
那就是这些动物能看见的光
That's what these creatures would see.
它们可以看到四周物体所发出的热
They would see the heat expended by their bodies...in the world around them.
它看上去完全不同于看你我
It would look very different than it does to you or me.
为了看到星球的黑暗面的热信号
To see heat signatures on the dark side of the planet...
赋予了Eronel上食物链最大的一环
gives one of the biggest links on the food chain of Eronel...
courga一个狡诈的优势
the courga, a cunning advantage.
在它们的意识 动作 集体行动的方式里
In their sense, in their moves, in the way they act together...
活像是非洲平原上的豺狼
they resemble jackals in the plains of Africa.
它们结队而行
They move in herds.
它们是猎手 它们是掠食者
They're hunters. They're predators.
丑陋而讨厌的动物
Ugly little, nasty creatures...
它们会包围一只或一群peena pod
that will surround a peena-pod or a colony of them...
把它们给揪出来 作为自己的大餐
ferret them out, and that's their meal.
它们具有与众不同的能力 不管怎样
They have the odd ability, however...
不仅能在曙光区里看到东西
to see not only in the twilight regions...
用我们普通人一样的眼睛
with eyes like we might normally have...
而且它们在上方还有第二双小眼睛
but they have a second set of smaller eyes right above...
一旦它们进入黑暗区
that, once they move into the darker regions...
就是黑暗面
the nighttime side...
它们就可以逮住那个区域里的动物的热信号
they can now pick up the heat signatures...of creatures in that area.
这些只是可能生活在Eronel之类的
These are only a few of the creatures...
星球上的少数动物
that could live on a planet like Eronel...
然而 至少在眼下
but, at least for now...
它们只是我们想象的产物
they are simply a product of our imagination.
在科学上 我们可以坐在这里
In science, we can sit there...
想象其他地方的生命
and we can imagine life elsewhere.
但是要我们举例子 拿出数据点 事实上
But if we have examples, we have one data point, in fact...
也就是地球上的
and that's planet Earth.
因此 要是我们可以观察地球上的生命
And so, if we can look at life on Earth...
地球给了我们大量惊人的信息
it provides us with an amazing wealth of information...
那么我们就可以循迹找到别处的生命
that we can then take forward to look for life elsewhere.
我们有各种生态系统供我们研究
We have a variety of ecosystems that we can study...
我们可以审视其中的挑战
and we can look at the challenges.
生态系统里有些什么?
What are in ecosystems?
生命会面临那些挑战?
What challenges do living things face?
我们可以将这些原理用到外星生命上
And we can apply these principles to alien life.
为了了解如何去运用这些原理
To understand how these principles can be applied...
我们必须继续我们的星际野生动物游猎
we must continue our intergalactic fantasy safari.
我们离开了Eronel
We leave the surface of Eronel...
急速穿越宇宙322光年
and zip across the cosmos 322 light-years away...
来到一个新太阳系
to a new solar system...
一个假想的行星AG 143
and the theoretical planet AG-143.
AG 143比地球大 比地球大很多
AG-143 is bigger than the Earth, much bigger than the Earth.
它有一个美丽的环系统围绕着它
It has a beautiful ring system that circles around it.
然而更重要的是它是一个巨大的干旱荒漠之地
But more importantly, it is a big, gigantic dry desert...
其引力场
with three times the gravitational field...
是我们地球的三倍
that we feel here on the Earth.
一个人 在地球上重175磅的话
A human, weighing in at 175 pounds on Earth...
站在AG 143的地表
would step off onto the surface of AG-143...
就会重达525磅
to weigh about 525 pounds.
毫无疑问 生命也必须适应
Certainly, life would need to adapt.
但如何适应呢?
But how?
哈佛大学天体物理中心的大卫.阿吉拉
David Aguilar of Harvard University's Center for Astrophysics...
认为想象复杂的外星生命形式适应的最佳方法
believes the best way to envision...the adaptations of complex alienlife forms...
就是通过观察各种生物
is by looking at the variety of creatures...
它们已经进化到了栖息在我们地球上各种生态系统中了
that have evolved to inhabit the diverse ecosystems of our own world.
我们来到了北卡罗来纳动物园
We're here at the North Carolina Zoo...
因为目前在国内所有的动物园里
because, of all the zoos in the country right now...
这个是非常特殊的
this is very special.
它规模大
It is large.
占地大
It's big.
这里的环境重现了我们地球的各种环境
And the environments here duplicate the different environments...we find on our planet.
今天这里是我们星球上
This here today is a marvelous example...
生命多样性的绝妙例子
of the variety of life on our planet.
在地球生命多样性里面 吉拉尔认为
And within this variety of life on Earth, Aguilar believes...
支撑极其沉重结构的这些动物
that creatures supporting an extremely heavy structure...
成为了了解AG 143进化的理想模型
become the perfect model for understanding evolution on AG-143.
我们所说的适应了一个沉重世界环境的动物
When we talk about an animal...adapted for a heavy-world environment...
就是这个世界重力较大 就是它
a world with more gravity, this is it.
来看看我们在这里看到的
Look at what we have out here...
这原型的腿可以支撑庞大的身躯
the prototype legs that can suspend a huge body.
当然我们可以将它放低
Of course, we would have to move him down...
使其更接近地面
move him closer to the ground.
但是这就是我们所见到的理想状态:
But this is perfect what we would see:
矮壮敦实 不过这样的重量
Shorter, squattier, but heavy like this...
适应了一个重力较大的星球
adapted to a planet with much stronger gravity.
尽管AG 143的生命形式肯定具有
Although life forms on AG-143 have certain comparable characteristics...
地球生物类似的特征
to creatures on Earth...
但是它们的陌生模样是我们星球上根本看不到的
their alien faces are beyond anything found on our planet.
看出去一切良好
Everything looks good from here.
好 收到
Okay. We copy that.
声音良好
Sounds good.
恭候大驾
We wish we were with you.
要是有朝一日 深太空探测发现了太阳系外的生命
What if, one day, a deep space probe...
又当如何呢?
detects life outside our solar system?
外星人会是啥模样呢?
What would an alien look like?
为了更好地了解这些异界生物
To better understand these otherworldly creatures...
以及它们是如何进化的
and how they might have evolved...
科学家认为你必须首先了解
scientists believe you must first understand...
有关生命诞生的物理环境的
a few simple concepts about the physical environments...
一些简单概念
where life might begin.
在你关注遥远恒星周围的行星时
When looking at planets around distant stars...
有两个因素是我们科学家所瞄准的
there are two factors that we scientists zero in on.
首先是与母星的距离
First is distance to the mother star.
这决定了你获取能量的多少
That determines how much energy you have...
是否有液态水
and whether or not you have liquid water.
其次 质量
Second, the mass...
行星的大小
the size of the planet.
这决定着重力
That determines gravity...
以及你可能会看到何种生物
and what kind of organisms you may have.
在人们思考进化生物学时
When people think about evolutionary biology...
我们往往认为整个自然界充满了腥风血雨
we tend to think of the whole nature...
生物间 物种间
red in tooth and claw,
等等充满了达尔文主义的竞争
and among species and so on...
我们忽视了就是
that we forget that it's the physical environment...
物理环境塑造了生命
that really shapes life.
你所看得的何种重力
What gravity you have...
何种温度 何种压力
what temperature, what pressure...
何种大气成分取决于
what composition the atmosphere is...
是否存在着大气层 等等
if there is any atmosphere, and so on.
物理定律并未因你穿行宇宙而改变
The laws of physics don't change as you travel through the universe...
因此了解我们地球环境中的生物进化
so understanding how creatures evolved in our Earthly environment...
已经让科学家去想象
has allowed scientists to imagine...
假设行星AG 143之类的其它星球上
what life forms might arise on other types of worlds...
有可能出现的生命形式
like the theoretical planet AG-143.
AG 143围绕着明亮的F级恒星运转
AG-143 orbits a bright F-class star.
这个世界只有10%的地表覆盖着地表水
Only ten percent of this world is covered with surface water.
集中在沙漠之下的水囊里
And pockets of this liquid H2O...
里面收集了稀少的降雨
collect under the sands from the sparse rainfall.
AG 143的环境炎热干旱
The environment on AG-143 is hot, arid...
阳光极其耀眼
and the sunshine extremely bright.
因为那颗恒星是F级恒星 所以
Now, because the star is an F-class star, okay...
比太阳更亮
which is brighter than the Sun...
你会接受到紫外线
you're going to have a UV output, ultraviolet light output.
因此那里的生物
So, the organisms there...
将不得不以某种方式来保护
are going to have to somehow be shielded...
不是大气层就是它们自己的遮蔽物
either in the atmosphere or in their own coverings.
这些遮蔽物可能是厚厚的壳
These coverings may be in the form of thick shells...
或其它外衣 来吸收强烈的紫外线辐射
or other exteriors that would absorb the harsh UV radiation.
但是AG 143上的生物
But the creatures on AG-143...
也会进化出其它身体特性
would also develop other physical characteristics...
是那个世界特有的
that are unique to this world.
这真是有趣的想象
It's really interesting to imagine...
生命可能会喜欢上高重力的行星
what life might be like on a planet with higher gravity.
从微生物的角度出发
Well, from a microbe's point of view...
可能不会有很大的差异
there might not be a whole lot of difference.
所产生的差异
Where the differences would start to come...
就是你一旦登陆上去 举个例子
is when you go out and land, for example...
你就不得不为站立而烦恼
and there you have to worry about standing up.
噢 该死的重力 我只是
Oh, darn gravity, you know, l just--
它也有可能吸引住很高比例的氧气
It may also hold a much higher level of oxygen.
我只是无法站立起来
I just can't pull myself up.
然而强大重力的另一个副作用
But another byproduct of strong gravity...
有可能让AG 143上的山丘
may also give rise to an unlikely cast of characters...
具有难以置信的地貌特征
on the surface of AG-143...
更确切说 是略高于地表
or rather, slightly above the surface.
地球上 我们的大气是79%的氮气
On Earth, our atmosphere is 79 percent nitrogen...
20%的氧气 1%的其他气体
twenty percent oxygen, and one percent other gases...
如此安排是因为地球的重力
that is held in place due to the gravitational pull of the Earth.
但是在AG 143之类的行星上
But on a planet like AG-143...
较强的重力会吸引住更为稠密的大气
the stronger gravity would hold a much thicker atmosphere...
完全适合飞行
perfect for achieving flight.
我们在2亿年前经历过一个时期
We went through a period...a couple of hundred million years ago...
那时 我们认为地球有过一个氧气含量较高的时期
where we think the Earth had a higher concentration of oxygen for a while.
我们从化石记录中看到过
And what we see in the fossil record...
大型昆虫 大型翅膀 大型飞行生物
is giant insects, huge wings, giant flying organisms.
因为只要你想一想
Because if you think about it...
你要有更多的氧来代谢
you have more oxygen for metabolism...
因此你做事要用上更多的能量
so you can do things with more energy.
那就像是
It's like taking in higher oxygen...
用氧气瓶之类的东西吸高压氧
with an oxygen tank or something.
你感觉整个上气不接下气
You feel all pumped up...
那就是这些生物必定的感觉
and that's how these organisms must have felt.
由于稠密的大气
With a thicker atmosphere...
和高浓度的氧
and higher concentration of oxygen...
AG 143的空中遍布大型飞行动物
the skies of AG-143 would be full of large flying creatures...
随心所欲长时间呆在空中
that could stay airborne for as long as they need.
一个例子可能是sargan
One example could be the sargan.
这种动物可能大半辈子都翱翔在空中
This creature would live most of its life...
寻找着这颗行星上
soaring through the atmosphere, looking for pockets of water...
零散分布的水源
that scarcely pepper the planet.
一旦sargan找到了出水孔
Once the sargan finds a watering hole...
它们会扑向水坑 不仅是饮水
they swoop down in hopes to not only drink...
还要捕猎那些
but hunt any creatures...
找到通向绿洲之路的动物
that may have found their way to the oasis...
如moblant之类的动物
a creature like the moblant.
乍一看 你几乎会把moblant当作海星
At first sight, you might almost mistake a moblant for a starfish.
它有短而粗的手臂用来穿越沙漠
It has stubby little arms that it moves across the desert.
然而关于这些手臂的怪事是
But the odd thing about these arms...
它们具有很长的触须来探测沙子里
is they have long tentacles that probe the sand...
可能隐藏的宝贵的水囊
for pockets of precious water that may be hidden.
这种生物的怪异之处
And the odd thing about this creature...
是一旦它找到一个好大好大的水囊
is if it finds a large, large pocket of water...
就会把水抽上来 就像抽水井那样
it begins pulling the water up like it's pulling it up a well...
它会一点一点增大
and it grows in size, and it grows in size...
把水储存起来 宛如骆驼那样
and stores the water up like a camel does.
适应了找到和储存水是生存的关键
Adaptations to locate and store water are crucial for survival.
要坚持在沙漠里
To be stuck out in the middle of a desert...
距离貌似有水源的数百英里范围
hundreds of miles from anything resembling a liquid...
将会是几乎所有地球生物的葬身之地
would be a death sentence for almost any Earth creature.
对于我们假设行星AG 143上的生命 情况也是大同小异
The same would be true for life on our theoretical planet AG-143.
这就是为何pholis的活动主要是在地下水附近
This is why the pholis lives primarily near the water deposits...
这样它就尽可能靠近在这宝贵的东西
so that it will remain close to this precious commodity.
AG 143上最怪异的生物之一就是pholis
One of the most bizarre creatures on AG-143 is the pholis.
它们短小精悍
They're short, squatty.
它是三条腿支撑一只嘴巴
It's a mouth supported by three legs...
下面的基座靠鳞片在地面攀爬
on a pedestal platform that has scales underneath.
它在沙子上滑行 宛如响尾蛇
It glides across tee sand almost like a sidewinder as it moves.
它具有感觉化学物质的超凡能力
It has the uncanny ability to sense chemically...
不管其猎物在不在附近
whether or not its prey is nearby.
它在溪流或小湖泊周围捕食
It hunts around the edges of streams and small, little lakes.
它一旦发现猎物 会突然停下不动
And if it finds its prey, it suddenly stops, freezes...
伪装自己 这样它几乎就变得分辨不出了 耐心等待
and camouflages itself so that it almost becomes invisible, waiting...
直到不行的生物过来
until a hapless creature moves...
然后突然之间 将其抓获
and then, suddenly, out it snaps.
它得到了自己的晚餐
It's found its dinner.
pholis的移动方式
And the pholis' method of movement...
在地面上滑动好像草地上的蛇
gliding across the surface like a snake on grass...
是另一种进化特征
is another evolutionary characteristic...
肇因就是这颗行星较强的重力
caused by the stronger gravity of the planet.
用鳞片爬行 而不是用腿
To slide with scales, rather than lifting a leg...
会比其它动物来的便当得多
would be a lot easier for any creature.
这提供的优势是其猎物远比不上的
That, and it offers a quiet advantage over its prey.
它们可能永远都觉察不到pholis的逼近
They may never hear the pholis coming.
但是作为AG 143食物链的一员 没有什么是高枕无忧的
But as the food chain goes on AG-143, nothing is safe.
潜伏在这些水池里是一种无声而致命的动物
For lurking in these pools of water lies a silent but deadly creature...
叫做heathor
known as the heathor.
在我们行将结束对AG 143的食物链考察时
As we end our examination of the food chain on AG-143...
我们看到了极端的挑战
we've seen the extreme challenges...
那里的生物对很少的地表水
that creatures on a world with little surface water...
和较强的重力必定要去克服
and higher gravity must overcome.
但要是行星的条件倒过来呢?
But what if the planetary conditions were reversed?
要是星球上对于生命来说有适量的水
What if a planet had a suitable amount of water for life...
但同时重力又很弱呢?
but also a much weaker gravitational force?
答案或许就在我们头顶上
The answer might lie right above our heads...
在地球的上空
in the skies above the Earth.
在我们的星际游猎中
On our intergalactic safari...
我们看到了主要的太空生物学家
we've seen how leading astrobiologists...
利用当今的地球科学来假设
used present-day earth science to hypothesize...
假想世界里的生物的大小 形状和行为
about the size, shape, and behavior of creatures...
那里的重力要比地球强得多
on an imaginary world with much stronger gravity than Earth.
但是如果重力弱很多 情况又当如何呢?
But what would happen if the gravity was much weaker?
为了找到答案 我们离开强重力的AG 143
To find out, we lift off from the strong gravity of AG-143...
前往89光年外的另一颗行星GP C 925
to another planet 89 light-years away, GP-C 925.
GP C 925比地球小
GP-C 925 is smaller than the Earth.
它是地球大小的一半
It's about half the size of the Earth.
它是地球类行星的分水岭
It's borderline for an Earth-like planet.
因为它较小 所以重力也弱
And because it's smaller, it has less gravity.
它所围绕的恒星温度要比太阳低
The star that it circles around is cooler than our Sun.
正因为如此 在冰冻区域
And because of that, it's a cross between frozen ice patches...
绿色光合植物探头的地方
green photosynthetic plants peeking through...
和水体之间有个交叉
and some bodies of water.
这里看上去极像我们地球的北部
It would look very much like the northern part of our planet...
靠近加拿大和格林兰的北部
you get up towards the northern parts of Canada and Greenland.
我们管那里叫针叶林地区
We call it the taiga areas.
GP C 925有一个非常特殊的环境
GP-C 925 would be a very specific type of environment.
你在这个星球上看不到沙漠
You wouldn't find deserts on this world.
实际上 你在这个星球上很少能看到山脉
You'd find very few mountains, actually, on this world.
这是个非常寒冷的世界
It would be a world that was cooler...
保存要易于我们自己的星球
more preserved than what we see on our own planet...
但是美景却无二致
but beautiful just the same.
这个星球 由于重力要小得多
This world, with much lower gravity...
就会产生更大 更优美的生命形式
could generate much larger, more elegant life forms.
我身高6英尺6英寸
Now, I'm 6' 6".
想象一下 我在只有一半或三分之一重力的世界里
Imagine how tall l could be if l had evolved...
身高会有多少
in a world with a half or a third the gravity.
想象一下 红杉在低重力世界里
Imagine what a redwood would look like...
会是什么样子
in a world with lower gravity.
作用于地表生命的此类重力效应
These types of gravitational effects on the surface life...
将会塑造出不同的特色
would shape and model different characteristics.
这也会反映在GP C 925之类的星球上
It would also appear that on a world like GP-C 925...
很大程度上 地表生命根本就不会在地表发现
much of that surface life would not be found on the surface at all.
我们现在是在鸟笼里
Here we are in the aviary.
高踞这些树上的是恐龙的残余
Up in these trees are the remnants of the dinosaurs.
那就是恐龙消亡后留下的
This was what was left behind when the dinosaurs passed on.
这些鸟注定是高飞的
These birds are meant to fly.
它们的骨骼是空的 它们的羽毛紧贴在一起
Their bones are hollow, their feathers locked together.
这些鸟注定要统治天空
These birds were meant to rule the skies.
但是在低重力星球上
But on a low-gravity planet...
这就是你会见到的统治天空的东西
this is what you would see that would rule the planet.
因为重力将变得较轻 飞翔将变得非常容易
Because gravity is going to be light, flight is going to be very easy.
飞翔将会像地球上一些生物
And flight is something that's been done on Earth...
各显神通的家常便饭
by a number of organisms in different ways.
蝙蝠张开它们脚趾之间的膜
Bats stretch membranes between their fingers...
变成翅膀来飞翔
and create wings to fly.
飞鼠展开它们的皮襟翼
Flying squirrels put flaps out of their fur...
一路滑行
and glide that way.
然而并非GP C 925上的一切
But not everything on GP-C 925...
都类似于地球上的生物
is comparable to creatures on Earth.
能够想象出来的最奇怪的飞行生物
The strangest of the airborne creatures one could imagine...
是lollygar
are the lollygars.
想象中的漂浮的囊袋几乎就像是充足气的肺囊
Imagine floating sacs that almost look like inflated lungs...
有很长很长的触须下垂
with long, long, long tentacles hanging down...
在背景中缓慢漂浮时
that drape along the countryside...
一直垂落到地面
as they slowly move and float over the scenery.
靠内部加热 温暖的气体将其囊袋膨胀
Heated by internal heat inside, the warm air inflates their sacs.
它们看上去几乎就像是水母 漂浮在空中
They almost look like jellyfish, floating through the air.
和水母一般 它们蛰刺捕食
And like jellyfish, they sting and grab anything...
面前来不及躲避的一切东西
that scurries over the ground in front of them.
来看一下它们随风飘荡
To see them moving, bobbing up and down in the wind...
就像一群迷幻水母那样
like a herd of psychedelic jellyfish...
是我们难以想象的
is something beyond what we can imagine.
而在这里 那是再平常不过的事情了
And yet here, it's quite common.
即使身临其境
Even life on the ground...
也会超越我们已知科学的极限
would push the limits of science as we know it.
我们观察这个世界时 不妨来考量一下这些swaystack
When we take a look at this world, think of the swaystacks.
它们看上去好像有长长的主茎
They look like they're long stalks...
伸向15 20 30英尺高的空中
that extend 15, 20, 30 feet into the air...
好多个在其顶端有一个灯泡
numerous ones coming up with a bulb on the end.
它们在风中摇摆
They sway in the wind.
然而惊奇的是它们并非植物
But what's amazing is these aren't plants.
它们是有根的动物 让其生根 缓缓走过星球表面
These are animals with roots that pick up and slowly move...
并将自己拴住
across the planet surface and anchor themselves back down...
在风中飘荡
swaying in the wind...
等候着靠近的动物
where they wait for any creature that happens by.
对于靠近的动物 其顶端像小飞盘那样
As a creature moves by, the top of them, like little Frisbees...
快速刺入它的身子
shoot off and wedge into the side of the creature...
刺入它们的腿 甲壳 毛发
into their leg, into their carapace, into their hair...
瞬间致命
stuck for the moment.
一旦移动到新的地方 它们会降落
As they move on, they reach a new area, they drop off...
开始新一轮生长
and they begin growing all over again.
它们只是利用这些飞在空中的这些小飞碟
They're simply spreading their seeds...
来散布种子
with these tiny little disks flying through the air...
前提是它们觉察到有东西经过
once they sense something moving by.
在这个星球上 我们看到类似的情况
On this planet, we see similar things...
植物和杂草生长在一起
with the plants and the weeds that grow here...
但是并不妨碍它的个头和范围
but nothing to this size and extent...
我们的概念会把握不定
and the idea that we begin crossing plants...
究竟是类似动物的植物呢还是类似植物的动物
that look like animals and animals that look like plants--
这的确是个怪异的世界
this is a bizarre world indeed.
swaystack和lollygar之类的生物
Creatures like the swaystacks and the lollygars...
在GP C 925 将会享用到充分的水量
would enjoy an adequate amount of water on GP-C 925.
但是在一个有着更多水的 好多水的世界
But what would happen on a world...
情况又当如何呢?
where there was even more water...a lot more?
尤其是 在没有任何陆地的星球
Specifically, a planet with no land whatsoever...
一个水世界上呢?
a water world?
打我们开始星际游猎开始
Since we embarked on our intergalactic safari...
我们已经看到了Eronel星上achom 惊人的生命周期
we have seen the amazing lifecycle of the achom on Eronel...
AG 143星上模样怪异的pholis
the bizarre-looking pholis on AG-143...
以及GP C 925星上漂浮的lollygar
and the floating lollygars of GP-C 925.
所有这些假象世界里的这些假设生命形式
All of these theoretical life forms on these imaginary worlds...
都是科学家所创造的
have been created by scientists, based on knowledge...
根据是地球生命进化的知识
about the development of life on Earth.
然而这些生物又是如何诞生于
But how would these creatures have gotten their start...
这些奇怪 遥远的行星的呢?
on these strange, far-flung planets?
我们知道产生生命的必要条件
The requirements that we know have to be there for life...
就是根据我们所知的生命
is based on the life that we know...
我们所了解的
and the chemistry that we think...
导致生命的起源及演化的化学
leads to the origin and evolution of life...
就是含水或水溶液里的碳化学
is carbon chemistry in aqueous or water solution.
我们需要有氮
and we need nitrogen.
你需要某种能量
And you need some sort of energy...
因为生命 即使是微生物 都需要食物
'cause life, even microbes, needs food.
它们必须要有某种代谢
They've got to have some sort of metabolism...
因此你需要有某种能源
so you need some source of energy.
阳光作用相当有效
Sunlight works pretty well...
但是它并非唯一的能源 即使是在地球上
but it isn't the only source of energy, even on Earth.
数百年来 科学家认为
For hundreds of years, scientists believed...
阳光是生命能量的唯一来源
that sunlight was the only energy source for life.
但是在过去几十年里
But within the past few decades...
新的发现表明他们错了
new findings showed they were wrong.
在海底热水口附近
Boiling water temperatures...
所见的热水温度
found around hydrothermal vents on the seafloor...
曾被认为是与生命格格不入的
were once believed to be incompatible with life.
但是最近科学家已经发现
But, recently, scientists have discovered...
这些黑烟囱周围的区域
the areas around these black smokers are perfectly suitable...
完全适合水下种群的繁荣
for a flourishing underwater community.
取代了太阳 这些生物的能量
Instead of the Sun, these creatures take their energy...
取自这些出水口的高温 气体和矿物质
from the heat, gases, and minerals spewing from the vents.
这些高度顽强的生命形式就是所谓的嗜极生物
These highly tenacious life forms are known as extremophiles.
这些极端的嗜极生物拓展了我们的认识
The existence of extremophiles broadens our aspects...
即认为生物能做什么
of what we think organisms can do...
和了解生物能做什么
and what we know organisms can do.
换句话说
In other words, if you look...
如果你观察所有不同种类的环境
at all of the different kinds of environments...
我们就会发现在地球上
that we find here on Earth...
其范围会从极冷到极热
it ranges from extremely cold to extremely hot...
到酸 到碱
to acid, to alkaline...
几乎到你所能想到所有状况
just about anything you can think of.
几乎在任何地方 你都能发现生命
And just about everywhere, you find life.
整个地球都能发现生命的事实
The fact that life is found at all on Earth...
很大程度上要归功于我们在太阳系里的位置
is due in large part to our position in the solar system.
我们科学家曾经认为
We scientists used to believe...
为了让生命出现在一个行星上
that in order to get life off the ground on a planet...
它必须是距离太阳的宜居区
it has to be in the Goldilocks zone of the Sun...
不能太近 因为水会沸腾
not too close because water will boil...
不能太远 因为水会冰冻
not too far because water will freeze...
而是要恰到好处 有液态海洋
but just right to have a liquid ocean...
在其中DNA可以形成
out of which DNA can form.
啊 那种情景我们现在知道是错误的
Well, that picture we now know is wrong.
我们现在认为 即使是在木星这样的行星的冰冻卫星上
We now believe that even on icy moons of planets like Jupiter...
都可能有生命出现
it is possible to get life off the ground.
木卫二是木星的卫星
Europa is a moon of Jupiter.
它被冰包得严严实实
It's covered in ice.
但是在冰层下面 似乎有一个巨大的海洋
But beneath the ice, there is apparently a gigantic ocean...
或许在数十亿年里 一直就存在着液态水
perhaps stable for billions of years, containing liquid water.
因此这就让物理学家等不知所措
And so that sent the physicists and so on scrambling.
你怎么会在如此远离太阳的地方
How could you end up with liquid water...
现在 事实证明 这个概念是
Now, what it turns out, the idea is...
存在着所谓的潮汐可挠性
is that there's something called tidal flexing.
对于木卫二来说 潮汐可挠性的肇因是其巨大的个头
For Europa, tidal flexing is caused by the immense size...
以及木星的引力
and gravitational pull of Jupiter...
引起了卫星上的冰拉伸
which causes the ice on the moon...
产生了热量
to pull and stretch, generating heat.
一旦下面的冰层得到足够的热量
Once the insulated lower layers get warm enough...
冰就会融化 变成海洋
the ice will melt, creating oceans.
现在加入被认为可以在
Now add the types of organic compounds...
木卫二上生存的生物种群
that are believed to exist on Europa...
你只需稍加改进 但又是对生命非常现实的手段
and you've got a slightly altered, but very realistic recipe for life.
这就把我们带去了星际游猎的下一站
This brings us to our next stop in our intergalactic safari.
我们离开GP C 925背后热闹的星空后
As we leave the busy skies of GP-C 925 behind...
我们走过72光年
we can travel 72 light-years...
来到一颗假想的气体巨星 叫做Yeneer g
to a theoretical gas giant known as Yeneer g...
有着8颗卫星的行星
a planet circled by eight moons.
通常 我们不会理会Yeneer g
Normally, we wouldn't bother with Yeneer g.
它是颗气体巨星
lt's a gas giant...
我们不认为生命会存在于这些星球上
and we don't think life could exist on these worlds.
我们感兴趣的星球是其卫星Aner'bas
The world we're interested in is the moon Aner'bas.
其大小是水星的两倍
It's about twice the size of Mercury.
它是个非常类似于围绕木星的
It's a world very similar to the moon Europa...
木卫二的星球
that circles around Jupiter.
想象一下 一个行星覆盖了海洋
Imagine a planet covered with oceans...
在其表面 有冰 大量的冰
and on the surface, ice, a lot of ice...
把一切都锁定在里面
that locks everything inside.
这个星球上没有踏足之地
There's no ground to walk on this planet.
然而就在这些海洋里 有可能充满了生命
But inside these oceans, they could be teeming with life.
由于Yeneer g持续不断的牵引
And with the constant pull by Yeneer g...
Aner'bas既有可能具有
Aner'bas would most likely have...
大量的地热活动
a large amount of geothermal activity...
那可能是生命诞生的主要能源
that could be a prime source of energy for life to begin.
Aner'bas的表面极少量的光
Near the surface on Aner'bas, small amounts of light...
有可能透过薄冰层渗入下面的水中
may bleed through the thinner areas of ice to the water below.
这里某些生物有可能已经进化成了眼状物
Here some creatures may have evolved eyes.
这可能提供给了它们有利条件
This may provide them with advantages...
但是也会让它们对某些防御技术更加敏感
but would also make them vulnerable to certain defense techniques.
amabo堪称狡猾的
One example of a cunning underwater escape artist...
水下逃脱大师楷模
is the amabos.
对我们来说 光就是光
To us, light is just light.
然而来看看amabo
But think of the amabos.
小巧玲珑 几乎是胶状模样的动物
A small, little, almost gelatinous-looking creature...
在水下游动 无忧无虑
that swims through the water, innocent.
假如有什么靠近它 威胁它
If anything comes close to it that threatens it...
它就会发出耀眼的闪光笼罩自己
it throws out a brilliant flash of sparkling lights all around it...
让靠近自己的动物眼花缭乱 不能自拔
blinding whatever creature came up to it.
就在那一刻 它逃之夭夭
And in that moment, it's gone...
犹如墨鱼喷出大大的墨水团一般
much like a squid might shoot out a big ink cloud...
它突然之间被耀眼的闪光笼罩
It is suddenly masked by brilliant lights...
几乎就像是国庆日的烟花
that almost look like the Fourth of July.
它逃之夭夭
And it's gone.
光 在那种场合 就是一种防卫机制
Light, in that sense, is a protective mechanism.
但是生活在深海里的生物
But creatures that live much deeper in the oceans...
会有其他的生存方式
would adapt other methods for survival.
一个例子是zowalina
One example is the zowalina.
zowalina就像是
The zowalina look like a cross...
可怕的蜘蛛和奇怪的螃蟹的杂交种
between a weird, weird spider and a very strange crab.
但是它们具有奇异的能力
But they have an odd, odd ability.
它们不是通过眼睛来感受世界
They don't sense their world through eyes.
它们不是通过耳朵来感受世界
They don't sense their world through ears.
它们感受世界是通过电场
They sense their world through an electric field...
它们身体周围所产生的电场
that they generate around their bodies.
这个电场可以延展出去
This field can be stretched out...
因此它就会感受到周围的动静
so that it senses everything that's moving around it.
貌似它的世界受到这个电场的影响
It sees its world by what impinges on this electronic field.
有趣的是
And the interesting thing about it is...
它们一旦锁定认为是猎物的东西
once they've locked onto something that they think is prey...
它们就会静候其慢慢靠近
they wait till it draws nearer and nearer...
以迅雷不及掩耳之势发起攻击
and all of a sudden--zap.
一个巨大的电击 击昏猎物
A huge bolt of electricityjets out, stuns their prey...
伸出触角将其抓住
and a tentacle whips out and grabs it...
拉入囊中
and pulls it right in.
它捕猎是利用电流
It hunts by using electricity.
在我们观察此类生物
As we see the immense challenges...
必须战胜水世界的巨大挑战时
that creatures like this would have to overcome in a water world...
尚有最后一个因素有待探索
there is one last factor yet to explore.
一旦到了地球人
When the time comes that the people of Earth...
探索宇宙间的生命时
discover life in the cosmos...
或生命最终决定自己暴露给人类时
or that life finally decides to reveal itself to the human race...
有可能它根本就不是生物体
it may not be a biological entity at all.
不是血肉之躯 碳啊什么的
Rather than flesh, blood, and carbon...
我们有可能会碰到钢和硅啊
we might be met with steel and silicon...
机器
a machine.
我们走近假设行星Gaia' Leo 我们的最后一站
As we approach the theoretical planet Gaia' Leo, our final stop...
我们注意到其表面有三个巨大的陨石坑
we notice three extremely large craters on the surface.
小行星撞击有生命的行星
An asteroid collision with a life-supporting planet...
将是灾难性的
would be catastrophic.
但是在Gaia' Leo上 情况会有所不同
But on Gaia' Leo, something's different.
我们近地观察
We approach the surface...
看到机械小生物到处在漫游
and see tiny mechanical creatures roaming around.
尽管我们经历了千里迢迢
Although our journey thus far...
发现在假想的宇宙边缘
has explored an imaginary edge of the universe...
充满了形形色色的生物体
filled with biological creatures of all shapes and sizes...
但是某些科学家认为外星世界
some scientists believe an alien world...
反而有可能是合成机器的世界
could instead be a land of synthetic machines...
就像Gaia' Leo那样
much like Gaia' Leo.
搜索地外智慧(SETI)中心的
Dr. Seth Shostak of the Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence...
塞思.肖斯塔克博士
or SETI Institute...
认为一旦地外生命被发现
believes that when life beyond Earth is discovered...
我们的宇宙较有可能是铁和硅构成的
our cosmic relative may be made of steel and silicon...
而不是血和肉
rather than flesh and blood.
任何已经足够聪明的外星人
Any aliens that have gotten clever enough...
都会建造无线电发射机进行联系
to build a radio transmitter and get on the air...
因此我们会听到他们
so that we could hear them...
有可能已经到了下一个阶段
have probably gone the next step...
这下一个阶段有可能是开发有思想的机器
and the next step might be the development of thinking machines.
要更好地了解
To better understand the origin of an alien planet...
遍布此类机器的外行星的起源
teeming with these types of machines...
科学家称我们只要看看地球上
scientists say we only have to look...
我们自己的智慧的进化
as far as our own evolution of intelligence here on Earth...
尤其是人工智能
specifically artificial intelligence.
人工智能 你可能会说
Artificial intelligence, you might say...
就是凭空制造孩子的科学
is the science of making babies from scratch...
而不是用传统的手段
instead of the old-fashioned way.
它尝试通过了解大脑的运作
It's the science and engineering that tries to put together a mind...
将科学工程组合进大脑
by understanding how the mind works.
现在 我们尚未达到这一步
Now, we haven't done that.
我们尚未打造出思想机器
We haven't built thinking machines...
但是圈内人士似乎认为
but people who work in that area...
那有可能在...
seem to think that that's likely to happen...
20 50 100年里问世
within 20 years, 50 years, 100 years.
可以想象未来数百乃至数千年后
It's conceivable that hundreds...perhaps thousands of years into the future...
我们可能会和我们的机器合二为一
we may want to merge with our machines.
要认识到在未来数个世纪里
Realize that in the coming centuries...
机器实际上会变得比我们聪明
machines could actually become smarter than us...
这样始终存在着危险
and there's always the danger...
我们的作品会将我们投入动物园 关进笼子
that our creations will put us in zoos, behind bars...
扔花生给我们 让我们跳舞
and throw peanuts at us, and make us dance...
就像我们把熊关进笼子跳舞一样
just like we make bears dance at zoos.
但是要是与机器合二为一
But instead of merging with the machines...
那么有朝一日 事实上 人类就有可能变成机器了
one day humans may, in fact, become the machines.
一旦芯片胜过了人脑
And once the CPU surpasses the human brain...
成熟的软件将会让这些人
sophisticated software could give these beings...
具有我们无法比拟的优势
an unparalleled advantage over us.
要是你具有了人工智能
If you've got artificial intelligences...
大脑的运行速度超过人脑100万倍
running on brains a million times faster than human...
思维快过人脑100万倍
and thinking a million times fast as human...
那么理论上它们干1万年 就只要思索上3.5天
they can theoretically do 10,000 years worth of thinking in 3 1/2 days.
巨大的能量将是他们实现这一壮举的生命线
Vast amounts of energy would be their lifeline to achieving such a feat.
一旦他们为了所有可利用的资源而获得了Gaia' Leo
Once they harvested Gaia' Leo for all usable resources...
这些小机器人生物 即所谓的seval
these small robotic creatures, known as sevals...
就会建造一条通向太空的星际高速公路
could build a planetary highway to space...
然后下一级的机器 捕捞器
then the next level of machines, the fishers...
将可以为自己的生存
would have access to virtually an unlimited amount of energy...
获得几乎无极限的能量
for their survival.
要认识到地球只是利用了
Just realize that the Earth only uses...
太阳能量的很少一部分
a tiny fraction of the energy from the Sun.
如果太阳这么大
If the Sun were this big...
地球相对太阳的个头
the Earth would be nothing but a head of a pin...
就只有针头那么大
compared to the size of the Sun...
因此我们只吸收了太阳发出的能量极小一丁点
so we absorb only the tiniest fraction of energy from the Sun.
为了获得太阳发出的能量
To harvest the energy from the Sun...
一个叫做戴森球的理论结构
a theoretical structure known as a Dyson sphere...
围绕它或其它所有的恒星周围构建起来
could be built around it or any other star.
戴森球是一个巨形球体
A Dyson sphere is a gigantic sphere...
围绕着恒星构建
that is built to surround a star...
以吸收那颗恒星所有的能量
to absorb all the energy from that star.
这样 你就可以吸收恒星在这个过程中
In this way, you can absorb the entire output of a star...
没有燃烧的全部输出
without getting burned in the process.
一旦恒星分解 能量耗尽
Once a star is dissected for parts and its energy is depleted...
捕捞器就会拆卸戴森球
the fishers could dismantle the sphere...
自己推进到下一个星系组
and propel themselves towards the next galactic battery.
如果科学家说的没错
If scientists are correct...
这种机器的架设有可能就在
this rise of the machines may even happen...
基地附近的行星上
on a planet closer to home.
随着时间的推移
As each year passes...
新的科学发现
new scientific findings are being made...
正推进着认识上的突破
that push the envelope in understanding...
不仅是我们自己 而且还有宇宙间的生命
not only ourselves, but life in the universe.
那是一个全新的世界 或者更确切地说
There is a whole new world, or, rather, worlds...
是有待于我们去发现的世界
ready for us to discover out there.
如果宇宙其他地方的生命最终被发现
And if life elsewhere in the universe is finally discovered...
那么 恒星数量之多让我们确信
the sheer number of stars assures us...
一定会有丰富多彩 数量繁多的生命被发现
that there is a diverse, colorful, and vast array of life to be found...
陌生的面孔会多得超乎想象
and more alien faces than anyone could ever imagine.